<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>A Construct for Tinkering With Digital Text</title>
 <link href="/msc_project_weblog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/msc_project_weblog/"/>
 <updated>2021-11-15T12:57:17+01:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>Rebecca Rui</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Prototyping: Sorting and Selecting Links to Open Documents</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/08"/>
   <updated>2021-11-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>/08</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summary of alterations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The representation of linked documents  in version 1 and 2 demonstrated in the &lt;a href=&quot;07&quot;&gt;previous entry&lt;/a&gt; are discarded.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;The continuation of representing documents as nodes in Lateral Mode is potentially distracting and not particularly useful for opening and closing documents. Rather, the representation of documents are now distinguished in each mode.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Linked documents are no longer represented as nodes in Vertical and Lateral Mode, rather as icons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transition animations are divided into steps, showing how link properties change from Inventory to Lateral Mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;selecting-links&quot;&gt;Selecting Links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the previous entry, selecting a node in Inventory View opens a single document. It is also possible to open documents by selecting their links. There are two ways of opening documents by selecting links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Double-click&lt;/strong&gt; on links between two nodes opens the two linked documents, and all links are visible between documents.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Single-click&lt;/strong&gt; on links between two nodes reveals a menu of the tag links. Selecting a tag link will open the two linked documents and only the selected tagged links are visible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/selecting_links.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;icons-for-representing-linked-documents-in-lateral-mode&quot;&gt;Icons for Representing Linked Documents in Lateral Mode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hovering on a link in an open document reveals the linked document. There are two versions for how to represent a linked document: as an expand icon or preview icon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/preview_expand_icons.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-demonstration&quot;&gt;Video Demonstration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below shows how to sort links by selecting #Labels, and selecting links to open documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KkLsF9JbPdM&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Prototyping: Switching View Modes</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/07"/>
   <updated>2021-10-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/07</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While in Inventory View, selecting a node opens a document. Selecting another node will close the already-open document and open the other. There are two versions for how this might look and work.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-inventory-view-to-lateral-mode&quot;&gt;From Inventory View to Lateral Mode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/bp_select_expand.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image above, the linked documents are always visible and join in the middle of the open document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image below shows an alternate version in which the linked documents are only visible when hovering&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on a link in the open document (called Vertical View).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/bp_inventory_vertical_lateral.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both versions, if a link is selected within an open document, the corresponding document is opened, and the linked content items align (in Lateral Mode).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/bp_inventory_to_lateral.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;openclose-mechanism&quot;&gt;Open/Close Mechanism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in Lateral Mode, if another link within one of the two open documents is selected, the other document closes, and the corresponding document opens. This open/close mechanism allows traveling by links while retaining one document as the main document. The main document is always the document from which a link is selected. In the image below, the open/close mechanism is shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/bp_vertical_to_lateral.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/bp_lateral_open_close.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that only the first-level linked nodes of an open document are visible in Lateral Mode. As indicated in the last step in the image above, closing a document will hide its linked nodes unless linked to one of the open documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lateral Mode (as in the lateral reading strategy) enables checking the original context of a transcluded content item through deliberate action. Through the use of tag links, it is also possible to sort which link types should be displayed. This means it is possible to travel by a link path according to a selected tag (e.g., #comment, #elaboration, #definition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/bp_travel_by_links.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-demonstration&quot;&gt;Video Demonstration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In version 1 the neighboring documents are always shown, whereas in version 2, hovering on a link shows documents as nodes on the side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version 01&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/oI5o20Qpypg?controls=0&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version 02&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/je8Pt7bm3oA?controls=0&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-failed-attempts&quot;&gt;Other (Failed) Attempts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempts-at-visualizing-opening-a-document-in-inventory-view&quot;&gt;Attempts at Visualizing Opening a Document in Inventory View&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the video below, the links are visualized as vertical lines on each side of the document. The thickness of the lines corresponds with the number of linked content items. One of the drawbacks here is that there is too much information visualized simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mS90u173WOY&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below demonstrates a slow transition from Inventory View to Vertical Mode. The question here is, what is the best way to animate a link within an open document to a closed document. In this example, hovering on a link has the effect of extending the line to the content item within the open document, and the closed document (node) scales up. A drawback is that the scaling effect does not immediately capture attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-fDsP9OiBDU&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;attempts-at-visualizing-opening-a-document-in-vertical-mode&quot;&gt;Attempts at Visualizing Opening a Document in Vertical Mode&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in Vertical Mode, the selected link opens the corresponding document. The question is how the linked content objects should interact. In this example, upon opening a document by selecting a link, the linked content objects align, and the links fade out. The alignment of the content items may suffice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/5ClUV5wzWxc&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;endnotes&quot;&gt;Endnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;This is similar to how selecting a bookmarked URL in a browser opens a website, it replaces the displayed website if another bookmarked URL is selected. It is, of course, possible to open a new tab, but the difference here is that the documents can be opened in the same window, and the connections are visualized as links across the boundary of documents (similar to what Ted Nelson calls &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aus.xanadu.com/ted/TN/PARALUNE/paraviz.html&quot;&gt;Transpointing Windows&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hovering on a link to show (documents represented as) node in Vertical Mode is not particularly useful, since the size is only informative when seen in relation to other nodes. In the next round nodes representation is to be further developed. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Why Tinkering?</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/06"/>
   <updated>2021-10-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/06</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;✱ Still working on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-tinkering&quot;&gt;Why Tinkering?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By tinkering with digital text, I mean engaging with text as a process involving analysis/decomposition and synthesis/recomposition. In line with the historical examples given in &lt;a href=&quot;3&quot;&gt;On Interconnection and the Boundary of Documents&lt;/a&gt;, that means breaking a text into parts to create something new…&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Concept Design: Content Items and Link Types</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/05"/>
   <updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/05</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summary of alterations to the design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content objects re-termed content items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The tagging system is also applied to links (called Tag Links)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Additionally, layers and tag links can be untitled.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stack view is to be redesigned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-items-and-link-types&quot;&gt;Content Items and Link Types&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the definition of the concept of a document given in a &lt;a href=&quot;03&quot;&gt;previous entry&lt;/a&gt;, the intent here is to define what documents can contain and how links (and what type of links) can be established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A document can contain one or many content items (previously called content objects). A content item can be an image, a graph, or a (paragraph-like) text segment. There are two link types that can be established between content items, namely, those that are transclusions and those that are not transclusions. For the latter, these link types are established by means of a tag, which can include a descriptive title or remain untitled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transclusions&lt;/strong&gt; (––)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tag Links&lt;/strong&gt; (#)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/link_types_01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-transclusions&quot;&gt;1. Transclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transclusion links are created when extracting a text segment from one document and inserting it into another document. Traditionally these are called excerpts and typographically classified as block quotes or inline quotes, and the link between the “copied” and the “pasted” is usually embedded as a citation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to how Ted Nelson envisioned links in his hypertext system Xanadu, within the construct, a transclusion link is visualized as a line between documents. The image below shows the concept of transclusion on a technical level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/link_types_02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-tag-links&quot;&gt;2. Tag Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/link_types_03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Concept Design: Components and View Modes</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/04"/>
   <updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/04</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;View modes are different levels of perspective on documents. In addition, the two view modes differ in the components used for representing the concept of a document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inventory View&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At the level of the collection.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Two-dimensional node-link diagram.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Displays quantity of connections between documents.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stack View&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At the level of a selection of the collection.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Three-dimensional layers.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Displays selection of connections and distinct connection types.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Merge Mode&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At the level of content objects.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Two-dimensional frame.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Displays connections side-by-side or sequentially.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-inventory-view&quot;&gt;1. Inventory View&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this view mode the entire inventory is visible and represented as a diagram in which a &lt;strong&gt;node&lt;/strong&gt; denotes a document and a &lt;strong&gt;link&lt;/strong&gt; denotes connections of varying types (specified below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Node&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of a node reflects the number of content objects it contains (i.e. the size of the document).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thickness of a link reflects the number of links between the content objects across documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the image above, from Inventory View it is possible to select nodes to create a stack and enter Stack View.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-stack-view&quot;&gt;2. Stack View&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;stack&lt;/strong&gt; is made up of a set of documents represented as &lt;strong&gt;layers&lt;/strong&gt; that contain &lt;strong&gt;content objects&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_A.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stack&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stack can be thought of as a workspace. The inventory in its entirety may contain complex layers of information, and so creating stacks is a convenient method for engaging with complexity by making a selection of which to view in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of a document is represented as a layer, which instead of having a single title, has a single tag and appropriates its functionalities. In the image below there are four layers: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#MAIN&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#A&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#B&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#C&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content Object&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content objects are the parts that make up a text, of which there are many types: paragraphs, lists, emphatic phrases, titles, quotes, comments and so on. A content object can have any number of tags, placing it in multiple layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_B.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link Types&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image below there are several links between the layers. As defined in the &lt;a href=&quot;3&quot;&gt;previous entry&lt;/a&gt;, there are two general types of connections that cross the boundaries of documents: those that are transclusions (identical extracts in separate documents), and those that are not. In the image below, these two types are visually distinguished by dot-line-dot links and side-surface links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;✱ it is important that these are visually distinguished but the visualization is subject to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_C.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the links that are not transclusions, these are categorized according to whichever taxonomy people wish to develop within the construct, hence the appropriation of a tagging system. By example, in the image below, if content object &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ID_P2&lt;/code&gt; is a comment on content object &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ID_P1&lt;/code&gt;, then the layer could be tagged &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#COMMENTS&lt;/code&gt;. If the other two layers are separate references, these layers could be tagged &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#REFERENCE_X&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#REFERENCE_Y&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_D.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to display links only between a selection of layers in the stack. Upon selection, the stack is rearranged. In the two images below the layers &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#MAIN&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#COMMENTS&lt;/code&gt; are selected, displaying the links between them, followed by stack rearrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_X.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_X2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in Stack View it is possible to merge all or a selection of layers. The arrangement of the stack will determine how the layers are merged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-merge-mode&quot;&gt;3. Merge Mode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image below, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#MAIN&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#COMMENTS&lt;/code&gt; are merged side by side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_Y.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image below, only the linked content objects (between &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#MAIN&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#COMMENTS&lt;/code&gt;) are displayed side by side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_Z1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image below shows the option for merging the content objects sequentially. If another layer was included, the order would depend on the arrangement of layers in Stack View.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_Z2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>On Interconnection and the Boundary of Documents</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/03"/>
   <updated>2021-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/03</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;✱ Still working on the introduction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this text is to give examples of both analog and digital projects based on mapping and visualizing interconnection, and in so doing, come to an understanding of what interconnection is and the many ways it has been explored in projects throughout history. so though I am expressing discontent with transferring biases and conventions from paper media to digital media, I am not saying we throw away these concepts, but consider how the constructs that we create and embed in the digital realm can serve as reconceptualizations of those conventions to better reflect interconnection (by making them visual, categorizable, and interactive). questions are: which of the significant features of historical projects are valuable and convenient for working with text? how might we design the interfaces of such systems in the digital realm for working with text, based on the intercomparison of their connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In what follows, core concepts and ideas behind systems for accommodating interconnection are discussed and implementations are evaluated and juxtaposed to current systems, such as the World Wide Web. In so doing the aim is to to consider that “[t]he past, and the pioneers who shaped the past, may hold many suggestions as to paths [that] might be valuable to explore in the future and advice on the most productive ways to go down those paths” (Hopper 1998).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be the case that there are “vast potentials in electronic media that we still haven’t implemented, and we may be in danger of missing some of the greatest potential in electronic media because we mistake some situational limitations in technical development or project management for impossibility” (Hopper 1998).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;terms-and-definitions&quot;&gt;Terms and Definitions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A document is a container of content objects, which can vary in modality (e.g., text, image, sound). Taken from &lt;em&gt;What is Text, Really?&lt;/em&gt; by Steven DeRose (1990), content objects are what Charles van den Heuvel and W. Boyd Rayward (2011) call “information chunks,” what Ted Nelson (1999) calls “content items,” and what Ridi (2018) calls “information units.” In [1]traditional [2]conventional terms, a paragraph, for example, is a content object; a quote within a paragraph is also a content object; a list and a list item are content objects. In other words, content objects vary not only in modality (text, image, sound) but are distinguished by type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of interconnection, on which this project is based, denotes the various connections among the content objects within documents. As Nelson (1987) explains, connections can be internal or external to a document, stated implicitly or explicitly. For example, phrases such as “in the example given below,” “demonstrated in the image above,” or “stated previously” establish implicit internal connections. Explicit internal connections are content objects that by convention take the form of a footnote or marginal annotations — the content of which can be an elaboration of a term used, an example, a tangent, or comment. Explicit external connections are inclusions of one document segment into another (what Nelson (1980) coined transclusions) or some other direct connection by way of reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various terms across fields used to express the idea of interconnection. As Christine Borgman (2015) writes, “[t]he body of relationships among documents is sometimes known as &lt;em&gt;hypertextuality&lt;/em&gt;. Within semiotics and literary studies, the term &lt;em&gt;intertextuality&lt;/em&gt; is used to describe more abstract connections, “as in the influence of one text on the meaning of another”(Borgman 2015). Nelson (2015) calls it &lt;em&gt;intertwingularity&lt;/em&gt; which “expresses a philosophical position about cross-connection,” namely that “all subjects and issues are intertwined and intermingled.” By example, imagining a data model based on interconnection would be one that allows a many-to-many relationship among entities. Entities with many many-to-many relationships would form clusters, and clusters too could form many-to-many relationships to other clusters. Further, the relationships between entities can be based on (or describe, or establish, or map) various relationship types.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, interconnection here means &lt;em&gt;connected on multiple levels&lt;/em&gt;, and is used to describe the various relationships among the content objects of documents. Mapping these connections can create complex multidimensional structures, and how exactly these are mapped and visualized is shaped by the medium of the document. In what follows, analog and digital systems designed for mapping, visualizing, and accessing content based on interconnection are examined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interconnection-analog-and-digital-systems&quot;&gt;Interconnection: Analog and Digital Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early analog system developed for mapping and visualizing interconnection is the “compilation of Jewish Oral Law with its rabbinical commentaries” organized according to the Talmud page. Representing centuries of religious discussion, the Talmud:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;consists of the core texts, commentaries by various authors […] navigational aids (such as page number, tractate name, chapter number, chapter name) and glosses. Most of these glosses are emendations to the text, while others contain useful (or cryptic) cross-references. (Neumüller transcluded from Ridi (2018))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image below demonstrates how the Talmud Page is organized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/talmud_layout_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://murals.wbtla.org/uploads/2/4/7/9/24790045/talmud_layout_(1).pdf&quot;&gt;A Guide to the Layout of a Talmud Page&lt;/a&gt; by Joshua Parker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other analog systems include the Encyclopédie by Denis Diderot and Jean d’Alembert; Paul Otlet’s principles, methods, and model of a global network of documentation; the hypothetical machine the Memex by Vannevar Bush; and Niklas Luhmann’s notecard system based on the Zettelkasten Method. The most prominent example of a digital system is the original hypertext project Xanadu by Ted Nelson. These all share the conceptualization of documents as nodes that are linked through some mechanism and according to a system. In other words, these are examples of multidimensional structures. In consideration of the scope of this entry, three of the examples given above are examined in more depth:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encyclopédie by Denis Diderot and Jean d’Alembert&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The work of Paul Otlet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Xanadu by Ted Nelson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Encyclopédie is a system of intraconnections (i.e., a closed system of internal references; an intranet). Otlet’s principles, concepts, and models are based on interconnections and emergent structure (i.e., open system of references). Xanadu by Nelson is also a system of interconnections and emergent structure, but with consideration of the potential of the computer as a universal machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-encyclopédie-by-diderot-and-dalembert&quot;&gt;1 Encyclopédie by Diderot and d’Alembert&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various information technologies for mapping interconnection (non-)hierarchically were produced in the eighteenth century, ranging from atlases, encyclopedias, dictionaries, and suchlike. A prominent example is the Encyclopédie by Diderot and d’Alembert, which as Rosenberg (2015) argues, was an innovative system for its time. In its entirety, the Encyclopédie is a system of intraconnections — which is to say, a closed system of cross-references — “comprising 28 volumes, 72,000 articles by over 2,000 writers, and more than 3,000 plates” (Rosenberg 2015). Though the design incorporates ways for external reference, the Encyclopédie was conceived and meant to be used as an independent system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alphabetical structure is embedded as running headers throughout the encyclopedia (as seen in the image below), allowing access to content by headword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/encyclopdie_vol01_internet_archives_AMA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/encyclopdieoud01alem/page/312/mode/2up&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other examples include annotated diagrams depicting the contents and functioning as a visual index. A tree diagram from the first volume is seen in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/encyclopdie_vol01_internet_archives_tree_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/encyclopdieoud01alem/page/n69/mode/1up&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The textual and diagrammatic ways of mapping structures are hierarchical, as was the convention at the time. However, as Rosenberg explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Older encyclopedias were generally organized hierarchically and by subject. Theirs was designed to be navigated by keyword, to allow readers to enter and exit at any useful point. Additionally, their encyclopedia was hypertexted. Articles were linked in a web through a system of renvois or cross-references. The Encyclopédie also offered a hierarchical subject map, echoing the structure of older works, but, in the work of Diderot and d’Alembert, the tree of knowledge was presented as only one of several heuristics. (Rosenberg 2015)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, as the computer-generated diagram (seen in the image below) elucidate, an underlying structure “implicit in the system of cross-references of the Encyclopédie” (Rosenberg 2015) is a network structure in which there are many-to-many relationships among subjects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/diderot_encyclopedie_map_crop.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Diagram by Olsen and Blanchard (transcluded from Rosenberg (2015))&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two significant points the diagram elucidates. First, conceiving knowledge as fundamentally hierarchical is not “paradigmatic of Enlightenment epistemology.” Second, nor is it intrinsic to print. As Rosenberg argues, though the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;network diagram would not have been familiar to the generation of the Encyclopedists, the concepts behind it were. They too were thinking about intellectual phenomena in terms of underlying structures and aggregate relationships. (Rosenberg 2015)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum, significant to the design of the Encyclopédie:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A system of intraconnections.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Typographic embedded links.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple (non)hierarchical structures are mapped, both textual and diagrammatic in form, offering multiple ways of accessing content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-the-work-of-paul-otlet&quot;&gt;2 The Work of Paul Otlet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work of Paul Otlet — regarded as a pioneer of the field once called documentation that branched into what is now called information science (Le Deuff and Perret 2019) — range from devising the model called Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records in which entities are linked on multiple levels in the form of a network (Borgman 2015) to developing new approaches to organizing and accessing information by establishing theoretical principles of information. Otlet also explored how information organization might be in the future in the form of illustrations serving as metaphors of a global network of documents once media other than the book would take precedence (Heuvel and Rayward 2011).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to the Encyclopédie — a project regarded as in response to the eighteenth-century information overload (Rosenberg 2015) — Otlet’s work was in response to the problem of “the enormous growth in the number of publications, specialist congresses, and international exhibitions that began to occur at the end of the nineteenth century” (Manfroid 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Rayward (1994) formulates it, the problem that Otlet analyzed and explored solutions to was “how most effectively to create, maintain, and change institutional arrangements for collecting, storing, preserving, organizing, retrieving, and disseminating all of the recorded information that is-or will be-needed within society.” With that complex problem at hand, Otlet envisioned new approaches to storing, organizing, and disseminating information while accommodating expansive growth and extensive reuse. Some of the most significant aspects of his work are delineated below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conceptualization of text as modular&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Re-conceptualizing the Book as:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A global system of linked content objects:&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Based on interconnection and emergent structure,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;And the necessity of multidimensional linking of content objects.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otlet conceptualized text as modular — made up of parts connected to other parts (internal and external to a document). An appropriate system, according to Otlet, must therefore allow and facilitate establishing links between these &lt;em&gt;parts&lt;/em&gt; (content objects). In designing such a system, Otlet explored the re-conceptualization of the Book as a global system of documents. As told by Heuvel and Rayward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In a 1911 lecture on the future of the book and of bibliography, Otlet came back to the idea he had first expressed in 1892 and in subsequent publications: ‘The arbitrary division into lines and pages of the book in its present format, does not at all correspond all with the presentation of ideas’ (p. 291). He envisioned the emergence of a future format of the book in which ‘each intellectual element, in corresponding to a physical element, will create a structure such that any combination of ideas, notions, and facts will be possible.’ He suggested that this process can operate in so mechanical a fashion that in the future, the book will truly become a machine to think with (Otlet transcluded from Heuvel and Rayward (2011))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the two illustrations below suggests, for Otlet, the development of such a system entails &lt;em&gt;ripping&lt;/em&gt; content objects (representing ideas, notions, facts) from books and collecting each on separate paper cards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- %%&gt; The book in connection with the library, the Bibliographic Repertory and Encyclopedia. The three bases of the Global Network of Universal Documentation”—Dissecting the book to create a card system as an interface to the Global Network of Documentation%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/the-book-in-connection-with-the-library-the-bibliographic-repertory-and-encyclopedia.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Global Network of Universal Documentation (transcluded from Heuvel and Rayward (2011))&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another rendition, the formation, transformation, and organization of ideas are shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/otlet_raite_de_documentation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Title and Source&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;del&gt;The system must, therefore, also be designed to accommodate expansive growth and extensive reuse. For Otlet, this meant the capacity to both store and accsess content objects by links and metadata. In the image below, Otlet explored a paper card-based system to establish multidimensional links between content objects.&lt;/del&gt;[2]With this conceptualization of ideas, and knowledge more generally, Otlet predicated his system on having the capacity to accommodate expansive growth and extensive reuse. For Otlet, this meant the capacity to both store and access content objects through links and metadata. In the image below, Otlet explored a paper card-based system to establish multidimensional links between content objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/otlet_card_experiments.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Multidimensional card system (transcluded from Heuvel and Rayward (2011))&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Otlet writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To increase the number of sides, one might well abandon the rectangular form of the card and adopt a polygonal form, an octagon for example. For sorting and systematically selecting the ideas that have been classified hierarchically, the cards are suspended from their centre. The Book as a structure of cards thus takes a quasi-circular form and can rotate. [I]ts structure […] constitutes a Book—for it is still a book—that has abandoned the traditional form of linear text arranged according to a unique plan. It has been transformed in some way into a body with several dimensions, as many dimensions as headings such that different searches using the same graphic elements on the cards are possible. (Otlet transcluded from Heuvel and Rayward (2011))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Heuvel and Rayward (2011) point out, though the material manifestation of such a paper card system is “impractical for many reasons,” what Otlet is describing is an open system for mapping and accessing content, based on the interconnection of subjects. Beyond these experiments with paper cards, Otlet envisioned new approaches to accessing content and new visual representations. For example, in the image below, “Otlet uses the architectural metaphor of the factory to visualize this process” (Heuvel 2017).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/otlet_mundaneum.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laboratorium Mundaneum (transcluded from &lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a9/Laboratorium_Mundaneum.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though Otlet was inhibited by the constraints of working with paper-based technologies (e.g., books, paper cards, shelves, cabinets, and desks), he envisioned new ways of organizing and accessing information beyond what Weel (2012) calls the “order of the book”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sum, significant to the work of Otlet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conceptualization of text as modular; made up of content objects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developed a system based on interconnections; networked information organization based on emergent structure and new ways of linking those content objects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explored ways of storing and accessing content objects through experiments with cards and metaphorical visualizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-xanadu-by-ted-nelson&quot;&gt;3 Xanadu by Ted Nelson&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;!-- %%Who is Ted Nelson and what is known for%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson is most known for inventing the &lt;em&gt;back button&lt;/em&gt; and coining &lt;em&gt;hypertext&lt;/em&gt;. Since the 1960s, Nelson has been providing reformulations of the definition of hypertext in a series of publications in which the project called Xanadu is introduced and sometimes explained in detail. Though Xanadu has never been fully implemented, the many prototypes and writings throughout the decades have influenced several hypertext projects, including the World Wide Web, “as its own inventor Tim Berners-Lee acknowledged” (Ridi 2018).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- %%In brief, what is Xanadu?%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xanadu is a hypertext system — technically a piece of software that since its conception has been designed to run on a global network of computers, in which every single document is to reside (Ridi 2018). Documents are conceived as containing content and connections to other documents that undergo changes. To accommodate these basic features of documents, Xanadu is designed so that connections are visual links and all changes are stored and can be accessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- %%What are the intents and purposes?%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent publication, Nelson describes the purpose of Xanadu:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;to build a deep-reach electronic literary system for worldwide use and a differently-organized general system of data management [and with the intention to] import literary concepts into a redesign of the rest of the software world. (Nelson 2015)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- %%Based on what?%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much akin to the work of Otlet, the intents and purposes behind Xanadu are reflected in particular notions about the structure of ideas and how knowledge evolves. As Nelson writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The physical universe is not all that decays. So do abstraction and categories. Human ideas, science, scholarship, and language constantly collapsing and unfolding. Any field, and the corpus of all fields, is a bundle of relationships subject to all kinds of twists, inversions, involutions, and rearrangement. (Nelson 1965)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Nelson, it is this continuous evolution that a system must be designed to accommodate, which is achieved by having the capacity for new categorization systems and any arrangements of old and new content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- %%As Nelson writes:%% --&gt;

&lt;!-- %%&gt; To the extent that information retrieval is concerned with seeking true or ideal or permanent codes and categories—and even the most sophisticated &apos;role indicator&apos; syntaxes are a form of this endeavor—to this extent, information retrieval seems to me to be mistaken. The categories are chimerical (or temporal) and our categorization systems must evolve as they do. (Nelson 1965)%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, the structure of the system must reflect the structure of ideas, which according to Nelson is nonsequential, and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;indeed, our thought processes are not very sequential either. [A]s you consider a thing, your thoughts crisscross it constantly, reviewing first one connection, then another. Each new idea is compared with many parts of the whole picture, or with some mental visualization of the whole picture itself. (Nelson 1987)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In line with that notion of the structure of ideas, in his book Literary Machines (first published in 1980), &lt;em&gt;hypertext&lt;/em&gt; is defined as “nonsequential writing—text that branches and allows choices to the reader” (Nelson 1987). Whereas writing and structuring sequential text entails choosing “one expository sequence from among the possible myriad,” writing nonsequential text entails deciding on the “interconnective structure” — “where to put things in the searchable maze” (Nelson 1987).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on these definitions and notions about how ideas and knowledge evolve, for Nelson, it is crucial that a hypertext system stores (and makes accessible) the many possible link types and history of changes to every document. With that as background, some of the most significant aspects of Xanadu are listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- %%What are the main concepts?%% --&gt;
&lt;!-- %%List overview%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xanadu is a system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;With a multidimensional data structure, in which there are three main categories of dimensions:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Link dimension.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Alternate version dimension.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;History dimension.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designed for interconnected documents, in which the connections:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are categorized into two main link types:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Content links&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transclusions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are implemented as bidirectional visual links.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Expressed by two concepts:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transpointing windows&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parallel documents&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- %%What are the main concepts?%% --&gt;
&lt;!-- %%Explain%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Xanadu has gone through many revisions and different prototype implementations, but the core concepts have fundamentally remained the same. In what follows, those core concepts are examined, with reflections on some of the implementations, in juxtaposition to a familiar hypertext project, the World Wide Web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Nelson often criticizes, the structure of the World Wide Web (and other projects such as NoteCards by Apple developed in the 1980s), commonly conceived hypertext structure as “a series of text chunks connected by links which offer the reader different pathways” (Nelson 1980). The image below is Nelson’s visual interpretation of that structure, often referred to as &lt;em&gt;chunk style hypertext&lt;/em&gt; (Nelson 1974).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/nelson_ordinary_hypertext.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from Nelson (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this structure, links only go outward; none of the inward links are accessible. For Nelson, this is an oversimplification of the potential of a hypertext structure and what a hypertext system can be. In contrast to &lt;em&gt;chunk style hypertext&lt;/em&gt; is what Nelson calls &lt;em&gt;windowing&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;compound hypertext&lt;/em&gt;. Seen in the image below are instances of content objects in several documents, whereby the sequence is altered so that the structure is nonsequential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/nelson_window_compund_text.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from Nelson (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to the World Wide Web, Xanadu is a system that stores every change made to documents (contents and links), integrated in such a way that former states can be retrieved and reworked (Nelson 1987). Important to note is that people can choose whether those changes are local/private or online/public, as seen in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/nelson_public_private.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from Nelson (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a document is online/public, any changes made (e.g., if the author revises the content or other people reusing parts or creating connections) are stored; effectively, the history of every document is accessible to anyone. To offer historical backtracking and version control of all documents and access to the original context of reused content objects across documents, Xanadu has (beyond the conceptual dimensions) three main dimensions: link dimension, alternate versions dimension, and history dimension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/nelson_xanadu_document.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from Nelson (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hypertext structure of Xanadu, called xanalogical structure, is designed to accommodate two categories of connections between documents, expressed by the two link types called &lt;em&gt;content links&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;transclusions&lt;/em&gt;. Content links are the arbitrary connections that people (authors and readers) create as they engage with text. These are the link types that connect a content object, for example, a comment on another content object, to each other. Transclusions are reused content objects. Significantly, on a technical level (and by interactive visual means), transclusions offer a way to retrieve “the origins and context of quotations, excerpts and anthologized materials, and content transiting between versions” (Nelson 1999).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Transclusion is what quotation, copying and cross-referencing merely attempt: they are ways that people have had to &lt;em&gt;imitate&lt;/em&gt; transclusion, which is the true abstract relationship that paper cannot show. Transclusions are not copies and they are not instances, but &lt;em&gt;the same thing knowably and visibly in more than one place&lt;/em&gt;. (Nelson 1999)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, links are not embedded in documents (as with HTML, for example), which means creating links has no repercussions to the content of the original document. Content objects are never duplicated; rather, they are &lt;em&gt;transcluded&lt;/em&gt; — included in other documents linked to the original document. Every link is bidirectional, so every outward and inward going link is accessible and technically implemented as an overlay, much akin to “a cache, or an alias on the desktop.” This is significant because it enables people to create multiple overlapping links on the same document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- %%How was this implemented?%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast to the World Wide Web, in which links direct outward and are embedded, so that the interaction entails leaving one document to arrive at another, Nelson envisioned Xanadu as a system in which documents are viewed side-by-side with visual links, which he termed &lt;em&gt;parallel documents&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;transpointing windows&lt;/em&gt; [Nelson 1999].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parallel documents, according to Nelson:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;are everywhere, but are not generally acknowledged. There are relatively few explicitly parallel documents (like Tom Stoppard’s play “Rosencrantz and Guildenstern Are Dead”, which is explicitly parallel to “Hamlet” – showing events that occur offstage in “Hamlet”, and vice versa). But implicitly parallel documents are everywhere – the parallelism of commentaries, the parallelism of long and short versions of reports, the parallelism of translations, the parallelism of holy books [Nelson 1998].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engaging with text would thus benefit from having documents visually parallel, and with transpointing windows, which are meant to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;support analysis and detailed understanding – by parallel commentary, precise annotation and the explication of contents; by the facilitation of pinpoint controversy. These are needed not just in scholarship, but legislation, diplomacy, and anywhere that interrelated documents need to be seen. We need this visualization for side-by-side parallel documents (from holy books to legislation); for detailed explication, commentary or disagreement; for comparing successive versions of a document. (Nelson 1999)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Instead of deleting content from one place and plugging it into another (today’s distorted meanings of the venerable terms “cut” and “paste”), the author should be able to pull screen contents from old versions into new, seeing all points of origin and also seeing what contents have not yet been used. (Nelson 1999)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several prototype demonstrations of how the concepts of &lt;em&gt;parallel documents&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;transpointing windows&lt;/em&gt; might look and work. The image below shows an implementation from 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/nelson_cosmicbook.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from Nelson (2015)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another prototype implementation (seen in the image below), the linked content objects appear when scrolling (or as Nelson puts it: “all objects sworfing (swooping and/or morphing) together” (Nelson 2016).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:sworfing&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:sworfing&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/xanaduspace_2007.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from Nelson (2016)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- %%What is (are) the problem(s)?%% --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, a reasonable concern is how to manage the complexity that may result from people creating multiple overlapping &lt;em&gt;transclusions&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;content links&lt;/em&gt;. Moreover, there can be an infinite number of sub-categories within each of the two main categories of link types that can be created. Whereas Otlet’s experiment with cards is impractical in terms of implementation because of physical constraints, the problem of creating and mapping structures in the digital realm has to do with how to display and interact with the resulting complex information. As suggested by Conklin (1987) in his analysis of hypertext systems, this has been a central concern for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/conklin_fig11.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from Conklin (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson refers to it as the &lt;em&gt;framing problem&lt;/em&gt; (seen in the image below), to which he notes that “filtering links is a key aspect of front-end design [which] is a separate study in itself” (Nelson 1987).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:front-end-design&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:front-end-design&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/nelson_framing_problem.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Transcluded from Nelson (1987)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another implementation, Nelson shows how the data structure (xanalogical, but in the video referred to as ZigZag) can be visually and interactively implemented as a multidimensional cell structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WEj9vqVvHPc?start=199&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;✱ Insert reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borgman CL. Data, Metadata, and Ted. In: Dechow DR, Struppa DC, editors. Intertwingled. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2015. p. 67–74.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeRose SJ. What Is Text, Really? Journal of Computing in Higher Education. 1990;1(2):3–26.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Le Deuff O, Perret A. Hyperdocumentation: origin and evolution of a concept. JD. 2019;75(6):1463–74.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heuvel C van den. Building Society, Constructing Knowledge, Weaving the Web: Otlet’s Visualizations of a Global Information Society and His Concept of a Universal Civilization. In: Rayward WB, editor. European Modernism and the Information Society: Informing the Present, Understanding the Past. 1st ed. Routledge; 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heuvel C van den, Rayward WB. Facing interfaces: Paul Otlet’s visualizations of data integration. J. Am. Soc. Inf. Sci. 2011;62(12):2313–26.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopper M. Vannevar Bush and Ted Nelson Revisited. Hypertext in Historical Context [Internet]. MIT Media Lab; 1998. Available from: &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.mit.edu/m-i-t/forums/hypertext/hypertext.htm#missing&quot;&gt;http://web.mit.edu/m-i-t/forums/hypertext/hypertext.htm#missing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manfroid S, Gillen J, Phillips-Batoma PM. The Archives of Paul Otlet: Between Appreciation and Rediscovery, 1944–2013. Library Trends. 2013;62(2):311–28.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson TH. A File Structure for the Complex, the 134 Changing and the Indeterminate. 1965;13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson TH. Computer Lib Dream Machines. 1974.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson TH. Literary Machines: The report on, and of, Project Xanadu concerning word processing, electronic publishing, hypertext, thinkertoys, tomorrow’s intellectual revolution, and certain other topics including knowledge, education and freedom. 87.1. Sausalito, California: Mindful Press; 1987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson TH. Xanalogical Structure, Needed Now More than Ever: Parallel Documents, Deep Links to Content, Deep Versioning, and Deep Re-Use. ACM Computing Surveys. 1999;31(4):32.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;photonhunter. Ted Nelson on Zigzag data structures [Internet]. 2008 [cited 2021 October 30]. Available from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WEj9vqVvHPc&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WEj9vqVvHPc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson TH. What Box? In: Dechow DR, Struppa DC, editors. Intertwingled. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2015. p. 133–50.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nelson TH. The Xanadu Universe [Internet]. 2016 [cited 2021 Oct 28]. Available from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://xanadu.com/xUniverse-D6&quot;&gt;https://xanadu.com/xUniverse-D6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rayward WB. Visions of Xanadu: Paul Otlet (1868–1944) and Hypertext. Journal of the American Society for Information Science. 1994;16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ridi R. Hypertext. Knowledge Organization. 2018;45(5):393–424.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosenberg D. History Debugged. In: Dechow DR, Struppa DC, editors. Intertwingled. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2015. p. 91–103.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Van der Weel A. Changing Our Textual Minds: Towards a Digital Order of Knowledge. Manchester University Press; 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:sworfing&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The idea of viewing documents side-by-side is solid, but having documents fly in and out of view as you scroll is not. There should be an interaction step in between, in which the content is only opened through deliberate action. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:sworfing&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:front-end-design&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;It is my intention to contribute to this aspect of a much larger project. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:front-end-design&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Questions That Follow</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/02"/>
   <updated>2021-08-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/02</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The attempt here is to elaborate on the terms used in the &lt;a href=&quot;01&quot;&gt;previous entry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-meant-by-paper-text&quot;&gt;What is meant by &lt;em&gt;paper text&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of the terms &lt;em&gt;paper text&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;digital text&lt;/em&gt; is meant to emphasize the primary modality (i.e. data type) of the contents of a document, and the medium (i.e. equipment) used for its transmission. The contents of a document under the category paper text is primarily text and the medium used for its transmission is paper, which means it includes both manuscript and print. Though the contents of a paper text is primarily encoded language in graphic form, it variably contains graphics such as charts, maps, illustrations, and so on. In terms of engaging with paper text, it follows that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Text interpretation involves processes of reading texts, graphics, tables, etc.—be they external sources or one’s own text—and constructing mental representations from it. [And writing] includes activities such as creating visual-spatial representations, pictures, and graphs. (Zahn 2017)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, engaging with paper text requires familiarity with conventions developed for communicating about text structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-those-conventions&quot;&gt;What are those conventions?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the most basic level, an example of a convention developed for reading and writing text is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the use of spaces between words. Classical Greek and Roman texts were written in what is called ‘continuous script’, without spaces […] Gradually, an increasing number of design and layout aids were introduced: […] capital letters at the beginning of sentences, line breaks, and a variety of punctuation marks such as commas, semicolons, colons and periods. Also, concepts such as paragraphs and chapters developed into a standardized system that allowed the structure intended by the authors to be transmitted to readers familiar with these standards. (Bruijn 2015)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventions particular to paper text are those derived from what Weel calls &lt;em&gt;Order of the Book&lt;/em&gt; — that is, presentation and structure of text based on the form of books and defined by the format of manuscript and print (Weel 2012). Engaging with paper text thus require a familiarity with concepts such as a table of contents, chapters, running headers, page numbers, and the interplay between them. Some such conventions were inherited by digital text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-is-meant-by-digital-text&quot;&gt;So what is meant by &lt;em&gt;digital text&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A digital text primarily contains the modality text and the medium used for its transmission is digital computers. Operating under the premise that the medium used for the transmission of text yield particular constraints and capacities, relevant to the juxtaposition of digital text and paper text are the following distinguishing properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-paper-text-is-inscribed-and-static-digital-text-is-encoded-and-dynamic&quot;&gt;1. Paper text is inscribed and static; digital text is encoded and dynamic.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With text on the paper page, language takes a static material form. From a historical perspective, the materialization of language had a great impact on human cognition. In &lt;em&gt;The Mind on Paper: Reading, Consciousness and Rationality&lt;/em&gt;, developmental psychologist David Olson (2017) gives an analysis incorporating a historical account of the relationship between literacy and forms of thought. By his account, engaging with paper text engendered critical thinking and systematic knowledge (Olson 2017). Similar claims are made by Eric Havelock (1976), who in &lt;em&gt;Origins of Western Literacy&lt;/em&gt; establishes an integral relationship between the technology of writing and rational and analytic thought. By example from research within the learning sciences, Roy Pea (1985) discusses the form of arguments contrasting oral and written language and its impact on logical analysis. With text on the paper page, human memory capacity was extended, allowing an argument to be stored and directly available to the reader/writer to evaluate the relationship between its parts (e.g. premises, (sub)claims, main claim) for consistency and locate potential contradictions. With the advent of print technology in particular, there was a greater capacity for “precision in the transmission of detail” leading to a “much greater exactness in the representation of knowledge […] through the use of such typically typographic aids as tables and different typefaces, font sizes, and white space as a means of ordering information” (Weel 2012).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Uniformity, predictability, consistency, and standardisation were prerequisites for analytical and scientific thinking. (Weel 2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These effects on human cognition are related to the staticity of (and what it entails to engage with) paper text. In contrast, digital text is marked by dynamicity and modifiability. At a basic level digital text is encoded as a bit pattern (e.g. 1010111) representing a character unit (e.g. W). As Stéfan Sinclair and Geoffrey Rockwell (2016) suggest, these properties of digital text imply an infinite potential for rearrangement and restructuring through algorithmic play (i.e. move these bits here to there, extract only those bits, rearrange them according to this, then that, and put those here). At yet another level, digital text is encoded by means of a markup language, which entails “marking up” the structure of a text, the visual presentation and the metadata—all of which can be utilized in tinkering with (the form, content, and meaning of) digital text. Importantly, modification of digital text by tinkering with the code that transcribes the text can be done without repercussions to source content. That is, in the process of rearranging parts, transforming between formats, extracting and sorting text segments, annotating or performing analyses on those extracted text segments, and so on — these operations can be performed without repercussions to the source content. With paper text, such actions are enacted directly upon on the material, and so additional information (e.g. annotations, symbols, citations, footnotes, and so on) is conventionally congested on the same page, which leads to the second distinguishing properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-with-paper-text-an-action-is-direct-with-digital-text-actions-are-interactive&quot;&gt;2. With paper text an action is direct; with digital text actions are interactive.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When engaging with paper text any action is direct. That is, actions such as writing, underlining, erasing, cutting out, pasting in, folding, sorting and resorting, are in a direct relationship between the action, the operations involved in that action, and the perception of that action. In the digital realm, a command — which can be a key stroke, a tap on a touchscreen, a verbal utterance, and so on — can equate a near infinite set of (opaque) operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these distinguishing properties, digital text invites tinkering with its parts in ways that are infeasible with text on the paper page. Exploring the potential of these properties of digital text, based on the premise that all texts are interconnected, is the aim of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bruijn M de. From Print to Ebooks: A Hybrid Publishing Toolkit for the Arts. 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olson DR. Awakening: Reading and Consciousness. The Mind on Paper: Reading, Consciousness and Rationality. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press; 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weel A van der. Changing Our Textual Minds: Towards a Digital Order of Knowledge. Manchester University Press; 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pea RD. Beyond Amplification: Using the Computer to Reorganize Mental Functioning. Educational Psychologist. 1985;20(4):167–82.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sinclair S, Rockwell G. Text Analysis and Visualization: Making Meaning Count. A New Companion to Digital Humanities. 2016. p. 17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zahn C. Digital Design and Learning: Cognitive-Constructivist Perspectives. In: Schwan S, Cress U, editors. The Psychology of Digital Learning. Cham: Springer International Publishing; 2017. p. 147–70.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Introducing the Project and Detailing the Method</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/01"/>
   <updated>2021-08-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/01</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a series of weblog entries that function as snapshots of the research process. This entry in particular serves the purpose of introducing the topic of research, the research plan, and the scope of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Title&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Question&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Method&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-title&quot;&gt;1. Title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;del&gt;Tinkering with Textual Structures: A Digital Construct&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]&lt;del&gt;A Digital Construct for Tinkering With Text Structure&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]A Construct for Tinkering With Digital Text&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-question&quot;&gt;2. Question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What may result from undermining the biases and conventions inherited from paper text when creating a construct for digital text, based on the premise that all texts are interconnected?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-hypothesis&quot;&gt;3. Hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implication of interconnection is that every text has multiple potential structures, which a construct in the digital realm can be created to reflect. To that end, the construct must support activities for mapping, visualizing, and accessing different structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;del&gt;Paper text has always been confined by the media object used, be it a book, folder, pamphlet, or journal. Thus, c&lt;/del&gt; [2]Text has always been confined by the material properties of the medium used for its transmission, whether that be inscribed tablets of gold or clay, or be it handwritten or printed ink on paper. Bound by the material properties of books and other paper documents, conventions developed for mapping and visualizing interconnection in the ages of manuscript and print thus entailed embedding categories of information in the form of such concepts as footnotes and marginal annotations. Some such conventions have been transferred to the digital realm. Instead of embedding connections, a construct in the digital realm can represent such connections in ways that are not feasible with paper text. With that as a point of departure, this project entails creating a construct for digital text with the aim to re-imagine how interconnection can be represented. Mapping and visualizing interconnection within and between texts can result in complex layers of information. These complex layers of information are conceptualized and visually implemented as components in a three-dimensional space that can be made visible or hidden through deliberate action. In the three-dimensional space, it is possible to access both the hierarchical and non-hierarchical structures of the main text that have been mapped. By accessing the hierarchical structure—comprising content objects such as a title, subtitles, and paragraphs, without any other types of content objects visible—people can conventionally obtain the main points (e.g., introduction, main body, and conclusion). People may tinker with that structure by making other content objects visible. In effect, people switch between perspectives on the main text, which shapes their understanding. In re-imagining how interconnection can be mapped, visualized, and accessed within and across texts, the final version of the construct enables a tinkering approach to engaging with text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-method&quot;&gt;4. Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the construct is to aid [1]&lt;del&gt;thinking&lt;/del&gt; [2]working with text by supporting activities for mapping, visualizing, and accessing different structures. Within the bounds of feasibility, this project entails writing a text on the topic of interconnection, which is mapped and visualized in the construct. The end result will allow people to access what has been mapped. The following is a tentative outline of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1-conceptualize-the-construct&quot;&gt;Step 1: Conceptualize the construct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the blueprint step. It entails creating sketches of the components that make up the construct, including explanations of how those components interact. For example, sets of linked content objects (e.g. a paragraph, a phrase within a paragraph, a subtitle, a list item, a note on a list, etc.) can be grouped to form a single entity. Each entity — that is, a set of content objects — can be linked to other entities. The visualization and functionality of these components are tested in step 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2-write-the-main-text-that-is-to-be-implemented-in-the-construct&quot;&gt;Step 2: Write the main text that is to be implemented in the construct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main text introduces and defines the term interconnection, explaining the philosophical position it holds and providing historical examples of media shaped to represent how subjects are connected on multiple levels. Through these examples, the biases and conventions inherited from paper text are examined, including a discussion on the (dis)advantages. Tied in to that discussion is the potential for re-imagining how interconnection can be represented in the digital realm. In this sense, it results in a self-reflexive project. Throughout the process of writing the main text, small problems are expected to emerge. In response to these problems, interactive visual tests serving as potential solutions are created in the following step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-create-interactive-visual-tests-of-the-construct&quot;&gt;Step 3: Create interactive visual tests of the construct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such problem to solve could be how the interaction works, for example, how to switch from one perspective to another in such a way that the interaction supports an understanding that each perspective represents an alternate structure of the same text (albeit, different versions). Another hypothetical problem could be how different categories of information are distinguished. If, for example, footnotes as traditionally implemented in paper text are abandoned, then how are these categories of information dealt with in the construct? And even further, how are different types of footnotes distinguished (e.g. a reference from a tangent, from an example, from a definition of a term)? The interactive visual tests created in this step are expected to lead to modifications of the construct on a conceptual level. As each informs the other, steps 2-3 are iterated until it is surmised that enough has been gathered for step 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4-full-implementation-of-the-construct&quot;&gt;Step 4: Full implementation of the construct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This step involves completing the main text and the design of the construct by making improvements based on what has been gathered in the previous steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-documentation&quot;&gt;5. Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each iteration of steps 2-3, the resulting interactive visual tests are documented and published on this weblog. Each entry contains the current version of the main text and the construct (i.e. the interactive visual tests described in step 3). A written reflection is included, serving to inform modifications for improvement. The final version of the construct (which includes the final version of the main text) is to be developed in [1]&lt;del&gt;Unity&lt;/del&gt; [2]a prototyping software and published online. To that end, there are two workflows. The workflow for publishing the construct entails (1) exporting the project from [1]&lt;del&gt;Unity&lt;/del&gt; [2]the prototyping software, which is (2) uploaded on Github for continuous deployment, then (3) pinned on IPFS via Fleek, and (4) accessed via a website URL. Hence the process of creating the construct is documented and publicly accessible. The workflow for writing the texts is designed so that a single editorial file can be converted to various formats. Thus, the texts intended for the weblog entries and the main text intended for the construct are all written in an extended version of the Markdown format, which can be exported into various output formats (e.g. HTML, TXT, XML) using digital tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-evaluation&quot;&gt;6. Evaluation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the documentation of the process and the final version of the construct inform the evaluation. The documentation of the process comprises written reflections of significant steps, and the final version of the construct serves as a demonstration of how digital representation of interconnection can be re-imagined. In order for the construct to hold the main argument, the following points must be reflected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the construct enable tinkering with the hierarchical presentation of the main text?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does accessing those different structures reflect switching between perspectives on the main text?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;[1]&lt;del&gt;Are there potential advantages to how switching between perspectives is implemented?&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evaluation thus contends whether or not the construct demonstrates the above points. Functioning as a preliminary list, additions and modifications are expected throughout the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
