<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>A Construct for Tinkering With Digital Text</title>
 <link href="/msc_project_weblog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/msc_project_weblog/"/>
 <updated>2021-09-22T20:39:18+02:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>Rebecca Rui</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Alterations to the Design</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/05"/>
   <updated>2021-09-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/05</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summary of alterations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Content objects re-termed content items.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The tagging system is not applied to layers but rather to links.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Additionally, layers and tag links can be untitled.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stack view is not three-dimensional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-items-and-link-types&quot;&gt;Content Items and Link Types&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the definition of the concept of a document given in a &lt;a href=&quot;03&quot;&gt;previous entry&lt;/a&gt;, the intent here is to define what documents can contain and how links (and what type of links) can be established.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A document can contain one or many content items (previously called content objects). A content item can be an image, a graph, or a (paragraph-like) text segment. There are two link types that can be established between content items, namely, those that are transclusions and those that are not transclusions. For the latter, these link types are established by means of a tag, which can include a descriptive title or remain untitled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transclusions&lt;/strong&gt; (––)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tag Links&lt;/strong&gt; (#)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/link_types_01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-transclusions&quot;&gt;1. Transclusions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transclusion links are created when extracting a text segment from one document and inserting it into another document. Traditionally these are called excerpts and typographically classified as block quotes or inline quotes, and the link between the “copied” and the “pasted” is usually embedded as a citation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to how Ted Nelson envisioned links in his hypertext system Xanadu, within the construct a transclusion link is visualized as a line between documents. The image below shows the concept of transclusion; how transcluded content items are encoded and rendered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/link_types_02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-tag-links&quot;&gt;2. Tag Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/link_types_03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Designing the Construct</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/04"/>
   <updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/04</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;components-and-view-modes&quot;&gt;Components and View Modes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View modes are different levels of perspective on documents. In addition, the two view modes differ in the components used for representing the concept of a document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inventory View&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At the level of the collection.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Two-dimensional node-link diagram.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Displays quantity of connections between documents.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stack View&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At the level of a selection of the collection.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Three-dimensional layers.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Displays selection of connections and distinct connection types.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Merge Mode&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;At the level of content objects.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Two-dimensional frame.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Displays connections side-by-side or sequentially.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-inventory-view&quot;&gt;1. Inventory View&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this view mode the entire inventory is visible and represented as a diagram in which a &lt;strong&gt;node&lt;/strong&gt; denotes a document and a &lt;strong&gt;link&lt;/strong&gt; denotes connections of varying types (specified below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Node&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size of a node reflects the number of content objects it contains (i.e. the size of the document).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thickness of a link reflects the number of links between the content objects across documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As seen in the image above, from Inventory View it is possible to select nodes to create a stack and enter Stack View.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-stack-view&quot;&gt;2. Stack View&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;stack&lt;/strong&gt; is made up of a set of documents represented as &lt;strong&gt;layers&lt;/strong&gt; that contain &lt;strong&gt;content objects&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_A.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stack&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A stack can be thought of as a workspace. The inventory in its entirety may contain complex layers of information, and so creating stacks is a convenient method for engaging with complexity by making a selection of which to view in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Layer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of a document is represented as a layer, which instead of having a single title, has a single tag and appropriates its functionalities. In the image below there are four layers: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#MAIN&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#A&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#B&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#C&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Content Object&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content objects are the parts that make up a text, of which there are many types: paragraphs, lists, emphatic phrases, titles, quotes, comments and so on. A content object can have any number of tags, placing it in multiple layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_B.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Link Types&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image below there are several links between the layers. As defined in the &lt;a href=&quot;boundaries-of-documents-and-reflecting-interconnection&quot;&gt;previous entry&lt;/a&gt;, there are two general types of connections that cross the boundaries of documents: those that are transclusions (identical extracts in separate documents), and those that are not. In the image below, these two types are visually distinguished by dot-line-dot links and side-surface links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;✱ it is important that these are visually distinguished but the visualization is subject to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_C.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the links that are not transclusions, these are categorized according to whichever taxonomy people wish to develop within the construct, hence the appropriation of a tagging system. By example, in the image below, if content object &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ID_P2&lt;/code&gt; is a comment on content object &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ID_P1&lt;/code&gt;, then the layer could be tagged &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#COMMENTS&lt;/code&gt;. If the other two layers are separate references, these layers could be tagged &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#REFERENCE_X&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#REFERENCE_Y&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_D.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to display links only between a selection of layers in the stack. Upon selection, the stack is rearranged. In the two images below the layers &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#MAIN&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#COMMENTS&lt;/code&gt; are selected, displaying the links between them, followed by stack rearrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_X.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_X2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in Stack View it is possible to merge all or a selection of layers. The arrangement of the stack will determine how the layers are merged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-merge-mode&quot;&gt;3. Merge Mode&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image below, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#MAIN&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#COMMENTS&lt;/code&gt; are merged side by side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_Y.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the image below, only the linked content objects (between &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#MAIN&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#COMMENTS&lt;/code&gt;) are displayed side by side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_Z1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image below shows the option for merging the content objects sequentially. If another layer was included, the order would depend on the arrangement of layers in Stack View.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/BP_Z2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>On the Boundaries of Documents and Reflecting Interconnection</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/03"/>
   <updated>2021-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/03</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;✱ This entry is the background research for the design of the construct. It will cover historical examples of dealing with interconnection, both paper and digital media.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Questions That Follow</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/02"/>
   <updated>2021-08-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/02</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The attempt here is to elaborate on the terms used in the &lt;a href=&quot;01&quot;&gt;previous entry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-meant-by-paper-text&quot;&gt;What is meant by &lt;em&gt;paper text&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of the terms &lt;em&gt;paper text&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;digital text&lt;/em&gt; is meant to emphasize the primary modality (i.e. data type) of the contents of a document, and the medium (i.e. equipment) used for its transmission. The contents of a document under the category paper text is primarily text and the medium used for its transmission is paper, which means it includes both manuscript and print. Though the contents of a paper text is primarily encoded language in graphic form, it variably contains graphics such as charts, maps, illustrations, and so on. In terms of engaging with paper text, it follows that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Text interpretation involves processes of reading texts, graphics, tables, etc.—be they external sources or one’s own text—and constructing mental representations from it. [And writing] includes activities such as creating visual-spatial representations, pictures, and graphs. (Zahn 2017)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, engaging with paper text requires familiarity with conventions developed for communicating about text structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-those-conventions&quot;&gt;What are those conventions?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the most basic level, an example of a convention developed for reading and writing text is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the use of spaces between words. Classical Greek and Roman texts were written in what is called ‘continuous script’, without spaces […] Gradually, an increasing number of design and layout aids were introduced: […] capital letters at the beginning of sentences, line breaks, and a variety of punctuation marks such as commas, semicolons, colons and periods. Also, concepts such as paragraphs and chapters developed into a standardized system that allowed the structure intended by the authors to be transmitted to readers familiar with these standards. (Bruijn 2015)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventions particular to paper text are those derived from what Van der Weel calls &lt;em&gt;Order of the Book&lt;/em&gt; — that is, presentation and structure of text based on the form of books and defined by the format of manuscript and print (Weel 2012). Engaging with paper text thus require a familiarity with concepts such as a table of contents, chapters, running headers, page numbers, and the interplay between them. Some such conventions were inherited by digital text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-is-meant-by-digital-text&quot;&gt;So what is meant by &lt;em&gt;digital text&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A digital text primarily contains the modality text and the medium used for its transmission is digital computers. Operating under the premise that the medium used for the transmission of text yield particular constraints and capacities, relevant to the juxtaposition of digital text and paper text are the following distinguishing properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-paper-text-is-inscribed-and-static-digital-text-is-encoded-and-dynamic&quot;&gt;1. Paper text is inscribed and static; digital text is encoded and dynamic.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With text on the paper page, language takes a static material form. From a historical perspective, the materialization of language had a great impact on human cognition. In &lt;em&gt;The Mind on Paper: Reading, Consciousness and Rationality&lt;/em&gt;, developmental psychologist David Olson (2017) gives an analysis incorporating a historical account of the relationship between literacy and forms of thought. By his account, engaging with paper text engendered critical thinking and systematic knowledge (Olson 2017). Similar claims are made by Eric Havelock (1976), who in &lt;em&gt;Origins of Western Literacy&lt;/em&gt; establishes an integral relationship between the technology of writing and rational and analytic thought. By example from research within the learning sciences, Roy Pea (1985) discusses the form of arguments contrasting oral and written language and its impact on logical analysis. With text on the paper page, human memory capacity was extended, allowing an argument to be stored and directly available to the reader/writer to evaluate the relationship between its parts (e.g. premises, (sub)claims, main claim) for consistency and locate potential contradictions. With the advent of print technology in particular, there was a greater capacity for “precision in the transmission of detail” leading to a “much greater exactness in the representation of knowledge […] through the use of such typically typographic aids as tables and different typefaces, font sizes, and white space as a means of ordering information” (Weel 2012).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Uniformity, predictability, consistency, and standardisation were prerequisites for analytical and scientific thinking. (Weel 2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These effects on human cognition are related to the staticity of (and what it entails to engage with) paper text. In contrast, digital text is marked by dynamicity and modifiability. At a basic level digital text is encoded as a bit pattern (e.g. 1010111) representing a character unit (e.g. W). As Stéfan Sinclair and Geoffrey Rockwell (2016) suggest, these properties of digital text imply an infinite potential for rearrangement and restructuring through algorithmic play (i.e. move these bits here to there, extract only those bits, rearrange them according to this, then that, and put those here). At yet another level, digital text is encoded by means of a markup language, which entails “marking up” the structure of a text, the visual presentation and the metadata—all of which can be utilized in tinkering with (the form, content, and meaning of) digital text. Importantly, modification of digital text by tinkering with the code that transcribes the text can be done without repercussions to source content. That is, in the process of rearranging parts, transforming between formats, extracting and sorting text segments, annotating or performing analyses on those extracted text segments, and so on — these operations can be performed without repercussions to the source content. With paper text, such actions are enacted directly upon on the material, and so additional information (e.g. annotations, symbols, citations, footnotes, and so on) is conventionally congested on the same page, which leads to the second distinguishing properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-with-paper-text-an-action-is-direct-with-digital-text-actions-are-interactive&quot;&gt;2. With paper text an action is direct; with digital text actions are interactive.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When engaging with paper text any action is direct. That is, actions such as writing, underlining, erasing, cutting out, pasting in, folding, sorting and resorting, are in a direct relationship between the action, the operations involved in that action, and the perception of that action. In the digital realm, a command — which can be a key stroke, a tap on a touchscreen, a verbal utterance, and so on — can equate a near infinite set of (opaque) operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these distinguishing properties, digital text invites tinkering with its parts in ways that are infeasible with text on the paper page. Exploring the potential of these properties of digital text, based on the premise that all texts are interconnected, is the aim of this project.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Introducing the Project and Detailing the Method</title>
   <link href="/msc_project_weblog/01"/>
   <updated>2021-08-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>/01</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a series of weblog entries that function as snapshots of the research process. This entry in particular serves the purpose of introducing the topic of research, the research plan, and the scope of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Title&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Question&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hypothesis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Method&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-title&quot;&gt;1. Title&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;Tinkering with Textual Structures: A Digital Construct&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;A Digital Construct for Tinkering With Text Structure&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Construct for Tinkering With Digital Text&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-question&quot;&gt;2. Question&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What may result from undermining the biases and conventions inherited from paper text when creating a construct for digital text, based on the premise that all texts are interconnected?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-hypothesis&quot;&gt;3. Hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implication of interconnection is that every text has multiple potential structures, which a construct in the digital realm can be created to reflect. To that end, the construct must support activities for mapping, visualizing, and accessing different structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paper text has always been confined by the media object used, be it a book, folder, pamphlet, or journal. Thus, conventions developed for mapping and visualizing interconnection entailed embedding different categories of information in the form of such concepts as footnotes and marginal annotations. Instead of embedding connections, a construct in the digital realm can represent such connections in ways that are not feasible with paper text. With that as a point of departure, this project entails creating a construct for digital text with the aim of re-imagining how interconnection can be represented. Mapping and visualizing interconnection within and between texts results in complex layers of information. These complex layers of information are conceptualized and visually implemented as components in a three-dimensional space that can be made visible or hidden through deliberate action. In the three-dimensional space, it is possible to access both the hierarchical and non-hierarchical structures of the main text that have been mapped. By accessing the hierarchical structure—comprising content objects such as a title, subtitles, and paragraphs, without any other types of content objects visible—people can obtain the main points in a conventional manner (e.g. introduction, main body, and conclusion). People may tinker with that structure by making other content objects visible. In effect, people switch between perspectives on the main text, which shapes their understanding. In re-imagining how interconnection can be mapped, visualized, and accessed within and across texts, the final version of the construct enables a tinkering approach to engaging with text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-method&quot;&gt;4. Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the construct is to aid thinking with text by supporting activities for mapping, visualizing, and accessing different structures. Within the bounds of feasibility, this project entails writing a text on the topic of interconnection, which is mapped and visualized in the construct. The end result will allow people to access what has been mapped. The following is a tentative outline of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1-conceptualize-the-construct&quot;&gt;Step 1: Conceptualize the construct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the blueprint step. It entails creating sketches of the components that make up the construct, including explanations of how those components interact. For example, sets of linked content objects (e.g. a paragraph, a phrase within a paragraph, a subtitle, a list item, a note on a list, etc.) can be grouped to form a single entity. Each entity — that is, a set of content objects — can be linked to other entities. The visualization and functionality of these components are tested in step 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2-write-the-main-text-that-is-to-be-implemented-in-the-construct&quot;&gt;Step 2: Write the main text that is to be implemented in the construct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main text introduces and defines the term interconnection, explaining the philosophical position it holds and providing historical examples of media shaped to represent how subjects are connected on multiple levels. Through these examples, the biases and conventions inherited from paper text are examined, including a discussion on the (dis)advantages. Tied in to that discussion is the potential for re-imagining how interconnection can be represented in the digital realm. In this sense, it results in a self-reflexive project. Throughout the process of writing the main text, small problems are expected to emerge. In response to these problems, interactive visual tests serving as potential solutions are created in the following step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3-create-interactive-visual-tests-of-the-construct&quot;&gt;Step 3: Create interactive visual tests of the construct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such problem to solve could be how the interaction works, for example, how to switch from one perspective to another in such a way that the interaction supports an understanding that each perspective represents an alternate structure of the same text (albeit, different versions). Another hypothetical problem could be how different categories of information are distinguished. If, for example, footnotes as traditionally implemented in paper text are abandoned, then how are these categories of information dealt with in the construct? And even further, how are different types of footnotes distinguished (e.g. a reference from a tangent, from an example, from a definition of a term)? The interactive visual tests created in this step are expected to lead to modifications of the construct on a conceptual level. As each informs the other, steps 2-3 are iterated until it is surmised that enough has been gathered for step 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4-full-implementation-of-the-construct&quot;&gt;Step 4: Full implementation of the construct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This step involves completing the main text and the design of the construct by making improvements based on what has been gathered in the previous steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-documentation&quot;&gt;5. Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each iteration of steps 2-3, the resulting interactive visual tests are documented and published on this weblog. Each entry contains the current version of the main text and the construct (i.e. the interactive visual tests described in step 3). A written reflection is included, serving to inform modifications for improvement. The final version of the construct (which includes the final version of the main text) is to be developed in Unity and published online. To that end, there are two workflows. The workflow for publishing the construct entails (1) exporting the project from Unity, which is (2) uploaded on Github for continuous deployment, then (3) pinned on IPFS via Fleek, and (4) accessed via a website URL. Hence the process of creating the construct is documented and publicly accessible. The workflow for writing the texts is designed so that a single editorial file can be converted to various formats. Thus, the texts intended for the weblog entries and the main text intended for the construct are all written in an extended version of the Markdown format, which can be exported into various output formats (e.g. HTML, TXT, XML) using digital tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-evaluation&quot;&gt;6. Evaluation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the documentation of the process and the final version of the construct inform the evaluation. The documentation of the process comprises written reflections of significant steps, and the final version of the construct serves as a demonstration of how digital representation of interconnection can be re-imagined. In order for the construct to hold the main argument, the following points must be reflected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does the construct enable tinkering with the hierarchical presentation of the main text?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does accessing those different structures reflect switching between perspectives on the main text?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are there potential advantages to how switching between perspectives is implemented?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evaluation thus contends whether or not the construct demonstrates the above points. Functioning as a preliminary list, additions and modifications are expected throughout the process.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
